ファイブ
フォー
(ｽﾋﾟｰｶｰ:管制官)５！ ４！➡
5.
4.
スリー
３！２！➡
3.
2.
1.
ワン
１！イグニッション！
Ignition.
(ｽﾋﾟｰｶｰ:管制官)リフトオフ‼
Liftoff.
(ｼﾞｮﾆｰ)兄さぁぁぁん！
(マット)イエーイ！
Bro!
Yay!
うう～うう～｡
(ﾃﾞﾆｰﾙ)見ろ ムッタ｡
Look.
(ﾃﾞﾆｰﾙ)リフトオフだ！
We have liftoff.
なんば　むった
Wow...
まっ まっぶし～！
It's blinding.
スリーツー　ワン
(ﾃﾞﾆｰﾙ)３･２･１｡
3.
2.
1.
(アポ)ワン！
Whoa...
《すげえ！なんだ この音！》
Crazy.
That was a huge roar.
Go.
行け…行け…行けえ！
Go!
なんば
ひびと
(南波日々人)うっひょ～！
はな
(ﾌﾚﾃﾞｨ)第一段ロケット切り離し！
Disconnecting first stage.
あ～あ 行っちまった｡
Yeah, he's gone.
あっ…けね～｡
That was quick...
着いたか？宇宙｡
Has he made it into space?
はあっ おほっ はっ ははっ｡
来ちゃった！
I finally made it...
Seven Days
Space Brothers
Before my uneasiness
was the end
of my happiness
I came to you
and we were one
Hello Hello
Let's fly
Here in this world we dream
and keep on dancing
Here among light and shadow
we keep changing
so that the wind doesn't let up
Even though the future is vague and unreliable
we are
not alone
#31 Rocket Road
だん
ぶんり
(ﾌﾚﾃﾞｨ)第一段ロケット 分離完了｡
First rocket stage disconnected.
だっしゅつ
続いて｢打ち上げ脱出システム｣を
切り離す｡
Disengaging Launch Escape System next.
(ﾌﾚﾃﾞｨ)第二段ロケット 切り離し｡
Disconnecting second stage.
(ﾌﾚﾃﾞｨ)さあ 宇宙船オリオンの
つばさ
翼を広げよう｡
Well, let's spread Orion's wings.
Okay.
(ﾌﾚﾃﾞｨ)ＯＫ｡太陽電池パネル
展開完了｡
Solar panels deployed.
とうとう…来たんだな｡
I finally made it...
宇宙へ ようこそ｡
Welcome to space.
(バディ)へへへ…あっけない
もんだろ｡ヒビト｡➡
Doesn't take long, does it, Hibito?
地上から ここまで
たったの８分｡➡
Half a minute from the surface to space.
飛行士に選ばれてからの道のり｡➡
But it took five years of training for you to get here, Hibito.
５年も訓練して待ってたのにな
ヒビト｡➡
来るのは一瞬だもんな｡
The trip just takes an instant...
It took a lot longer than five years.
５年じゃ すまね～な｡
２０年 待ってたよ｡こん時を｡
I've been waiting twenty years for this moment.
ハハハ 打ち上げは まだ
終わってね～ぞ ワンコ｡
The launch isn't over yet, pup.
もうちょい待ってやれ｡
Wait a little longer.
よいん
(ﾃﾞﾆｰﾙ)余韻ってヤツだな｡➡
You have to savor the moment.
あのロケットロードが
流れるまでの余韻｡➡
It's not over until the smoke clears.
それを含めて…
打ち上げっていうんだ｡
That's all part
of a space launch.
飛んでったわ お父さん｡
日々人が飛んでった｡
He took off, dear.
Hibito took off...
かんぺき
(南波父)ああ 完璧な
打ち上げだったな｡
Yeah, it was a perfect launch.
Perfect.
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)よかった｡
Hurray!
That was wonderful.
久しぶりにドキドキしたわね｡
I haven't been so excited in a long time.
うれ
(田村)嬉しいですね｡先生｡
You must be thrilled, Professor.
Yes.
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)やったわね あの子｡
He really did it.
そして次は…｡➡
And next will be...
楽しみね｡
I can't wait to watch that.
打ち上げを見たのは初めてか？
ムッタ｡お？
Was that the first launch you've watched, Mutta?
ああ ほとんど一瞬の
出来事だったな｡
Yeah,
it was pretty short.
(ﾃﾞﾆｰﾙ)ハハハハ！そりゃそうだ｡
だんがん
弾丸より速いんだからな｡➡
Of course it was.
A rocket travels faster than a speeding bullet.
ロケットってのは｡
《あいつ…本当に宇宙に
行きやがったな》
He really
made it to space...
それでは本日のメイン･イベント➡
Now, it's time for today's main event.
We have a message from astronaut Hoshide Akihiko, aboard the International Space Station!
国際宇宙ステーションにいる
ほしで　あきひこ
星出彰彦飛行士と交信をしま～す｡
おおお 来たぁ！
This is it!
では早速 みんなで
星出さんを呼びましょう！
Let's call for Hoshide together.
せ～の！
(子供たち)星出さ～ん！
Ready and...
Hoshide!
[TV](星出さん)
ジャクサ
はい こんにちは｡ＪＡＸＡ
宇宙飛行士の星出彰彦です｡
Hello, everyone.
I am Hoshide Akihiko, a JAXA astronaut.
わあ～！
すげ～！
Wow.
Hoshide is in space right now.
《今 宇宙に いんだよなぁ
星出さん》
[TV]今日は皆さんの質問に
答えたいと思います｡➡
Today, I would like to answer any questions you may have.
どうぞ よろしく｡
Please ask away.
Okay, who wants to talk to Hoshide?
はい では 星出さんと
お話したい人｡
Me! Me! Me! Me!
(子供たち)はい！はい！はい！
はい！はい！はい！
じゃあ まずは そこのあなた
どうぞ｡
Let's start with you.
Step up.
Yay!
やったぁ！
いいなぁ｡
Lucky...
What happens if you get sick in space?
宇宙で病気になったら
どうするんですか？
[TV]万一 病気になった時のために
じょうび
薬は常備されているし➡
There's medicine on the station in case someone gets sick.
救急処置ができるように
医学的な訓練も つんでいるんだ｡
And astronauts receive rudimentary first aid training for emergencies.
はい わかったかな？
ありがとうございました！
There you go.
Does that answer your question?
Thank you very much!
Who else has a question?
では 質問したい人！
(子供たち)はい！はい！はい！
Me! Me! Me! Me!
はい！はい！はい！はい！
(子供たち)はい！はい！はい！
じゃあ あなたどうぞ｡
Why don't you go next?
わ～い！
Yay.
Look at all the people here.
これだけ人がいるんだから
そう簡単には当たんないって｡
It's hard to be chosen.
No, I am going to get chosen!
いいや 絶対当たってやる！
Have you ever cried in space because something sad happened?
宇宙で悲しいことがあって
泣いちゃったりしますか？
What happens to your tears?
涙は どんなふうになるんですか？
[TV]う～ん 感動する事の方が
多いかもね｡➡
I'm usually too excited to be sad.
Sometimes, I'm so moved that I shed a few tears.
もし感動の涙が流れたら
重力がないから➡
And without gravity, they don't roll down my face.
目からこぼれ落ちるのではなくて
顔にはりつくだろうね｡
Instead, they just stay in place.
And there you have it.
ということです｡
ありがとうございました｡
Thank you very much!
Next—
では 次に…｡
はい！はい！はい！はい！
ちょ ちょっと！
Me! Me! Me! Me!
Hey...
ハハハ…すごいやる気だわね｡
じゃあ あなた｡
ヤッター！
You're really fired up.
Well, go ahead.
Yes!
See? I told you I'd be chosen!
ほら！
絶対当たるって言っただろ！
ほらじゃねえよ｡フライングだろ｡
That doesn't count. You jumped the gun.
では 質問をどうぞ｡
はい！
わっ！お おい…｡
Come ask your question.
Yes!
H-Hey...
こんにちは！南波日々人です！
僕 絶対 宇宙飛行士になります！
絶対って…｡
Hello!
I'm Nanba Hibito!
I'm definitely gonna become an astronaut!
Definitely?
それで 僕は
月に行きたいんですけど➡
I want to go to the moon.
Is there anywhere you want to go, Hoshide?
星出さんは行ってみたい星とか
ありますか？
[TV]いろいろな星に行ってみたいな｡
月にも行ってみたいし➡
There are many places I want to visit.
I'd like to go to the moon and to Mars.
火星にも行ってみたい｡➡
[TV]実は僕は 宇宙飛行士の試験に
２回落ちているんです｡
２回も？
By the way, I failed the astronaut selection exam twice.
Twice?
[TV]でも ３度目に受けた試験に
ようやく合格して➡
But on my third attempt, I finally passed and became an astronaut.
宇宙飛行士になることが
できました｡
へえ！すげえな 星出さん！
Hoshide's awesome!
[TV]だから 日々人君も
あきらめずに頑張ってほしいな｡
So work hard and never give up, Hibito.
Yes! Yes!
はい！はい！頑張ります！
兄貴のムッちゃんと一緒に➡
I'll do my best!
My brother, Mu, and I will definitely make it to space!
絶対 宇宙行きます‼
バカ お前っ！
A-Are you an idiot?
[TV]そうか お兄ちゃんも宇宙へ
行きたいんだね｡頑張って｡
Ah, so your brother also wants to go to space?
Good luck.
…はい｡多分…
僕は行けたら行きま～す｡
ありがとうございました！
Y-Yes...
I'll go to space if I can...
Thank you very much!
[TV]どういたしまして｡宇宙飛行士に
なった君たちに会えるのを➡
You're welcome.
I'm looking forward to seeing you become astronauts.
楽しみにしているよ｡
じゃあ また｡
(六太･日々人)バイバーイ！
Until we meet again.
Bye-bye!
Even if you don't want to go to space, I'm still going to make it.
ムッちゃんが行かなくても
俺は絶対 宇宙に行くからな…｡
君はアレだね 日々人君｡
Yeah, Hibito...
昔から｢絶対 絶対｣って
軽～く言っちゃうけども➡
You always threw the word "definitely" around.
But nothing is definite in this world...
世の中に絶対なんて
ないんじゃねえかなあ…｡
Sure.
そうだな…
世の中には｢絶対｣はないかもな｡
Nothing is definite in this world.
Huh?
But it's okay.
でも 大丈夫｡
俺ん中にあるから｡
Some things within me are definite.
The rocket road allows no detours.
現在 《ロケットロードは
寄り道をしない｡➡
There's no turning back, either.
後戻りもしない｡➡
It's a straight path up to space.
ただ一直線に 宇宙へ伸びる道》
Just like you, Hibito.
＜まんま お前みたいだな
日々人＞
キャンディなめるか？お？
Want some candy?
Houston, we have visual of the lunar module Queen.
ヒューストン 前方に
着陸船クイーンを確認した｡
Okay, go ahead and rendezvous with it.
ＯＫ｡ランデヴーといこう｡
I want to try docking this myself...
自分でドッキング
やってみたいな～ これ｡
We'll be counting on you when the autopilot breaks down, Hibito.
自動制御ｼｽﾃﾑがぶっ壊れた時は
頼むぜ ヒビト｡ハハハ！
Three meters to go.
残り３メートル…２メートル…➡
Two meters.
１メートル｡
One meter.
Secure.
捕獲 ドッキング成功！
Docking complete.
≪よし！≫
≪ヤッター！≫
Good.
(紫)バッチシ！
Right on!
(ﾌﾚﾃﾞｨ)それでは諸君…｡
Well, ladies and gentlemen...
(ﾌﾚﾃﾞｨ)月へ行こう｡
Let's go to the moon.
ＥＤＳエンジン 点火｡
EDS engine ignition.
(管制)司令船オリオン １０秒後
ＥＤＳエンジン停止｡
(通信:ﾌﾚﾃﾞｨ)了解｡
Shut off EDS command module Orion engine in ten seconds.
Roger.
Okay...
(通信:ﾌﾚﾃﾞｨ)よし 月軌道に入った｡
Trans-Lunar Injection complete.
≪よ～し！≫
Yes!
ＥＤＳ 切り離しスタンバイ｡➡
Stand by to detach EDS.
スリー ツー ワン｡
3.
2.
1.
(通信:ﾌﾚﾃﾞｨ)ＥＤＳ 分離完了｡
EDS detached.
≪姿勢制御も安定しています｡
異常なし！≫
Reaction Control System is stable.
All clear to go.
いいぞ オリオン 全て順調だ｡
ゆっくりしてくれ｡➡
Looking good, Orion.
Everything's going well.
You can relax.
あとは月を待つだけだ｡
All that's left is waiting for the moon.
ほれ そろそろキタろ｡
Here.
You're probably feeling a little queasy.
What's this, Buddy?
何だよ バディ｡俺が吐くってか？
気にするな｡
最初は誰だってそうだ｡
You think I'm gonna throw up?
No need to be ashamed.
It happens to everyone in the beginning.
俺もよく吐いたもんさ｡➡
I used to throw up all the time.
天地左右の感覚が麻痺して
目がグルグル回ってるだろ｡➡
Your sense of direction is out of whack, and your eyes are starting to spin.
That's known as spacesickness.
それが｢宇宙酔い｣というヤツだ｡
I feel perfectly fine.
何もなってねえけど｡
なぬ？
What?
そんなハズはない！
全然｡
That's impossible!
I'm good.
いて…何故だ？
Oh.
Why?
俺 今ちょっと気持ち悪いのに…｡
But I'm starting to feel sick...
Everyone, let's eat.
みんな そろそろメシにしようぜ｡
いいね！キャプテン｡
Oh, that sounds good, Captain.
(ﾃﾞﾆｰﾙ)メシを食おう｡➡
Let's eat.
お前のワンコに食われたからな｡➡
You know, your dog ate my food...
ワシのホットドッグ｡➡
Ate my hot dog.
犬の肉を
使ってる訳でもないのに➡
Do you know why they're called hot dogs,
even though they aren't made from dog meat, Mutta?
何でドッグって言うか知ってるか
ムッタ｡
Oh?
いや そういえば知らねえなあ｡
何でなの？
Actually, I don't know...
Why are they called hot dogs?
フッ…ワシも知らん｡ハハハ！➡
I don't know, either.
《何だよ！》
The hell?
(ﾃﾞﾆｰﾙ)これと あとミルクくれ｡
(店員)８ドルです｡
Can I get some milk, too?
That'll be eight dollars.
How does it feel to watch your little brother go into space?
自分の弟が宇宙に行くってのは
どんな気分だ？お～？
…そうだなあ｡
ほとんど今日の空みたいだったな｡
How...
It was more or less like the sky today.
最初はやたら曇ってて そのうち
中途半端な感じになって…➡
It started off cloudy.
Then it cleared up a little...
And now, it's sunny.
今は…晴れてる｡
なるほど｡ハハハ…空な｡まあ
人生もそうだ｡空模様と同じだ｡➡
I see...
The sky, huh?
Well, life is like the weather.
It can be sunny or cloudy.
晴れたり 曇ったり
雨も降りゃ 雷も落ちる｡➡
Sometimes it rains, and sometimes it storms.
It can be a pain...
めんどくせぇもんだぜ｡➡
ところでムッタ 空と人生の一番の
違いは 何だか知ってるか？お？
By the way, Mutta...
Do you know the biggest difference between life and the sky?
Huh?
いや…知らないけど｡
No, I don't.
ハハハ！ワシも知らん｡
I don't know, either.
I knew he was going to say that.
《…って言うんだろ～ぜ
どうせ》
The sky doesn't belong to anyone.
空は誰のもんでもない｡
人生は自分のもんだ｡
Your life belongs to you.
人生はコントロールがきく｡
You can control your own life.
ワシの名は…デニール･ヤング｡
だから知ってるって！
My name is Deneil Young.
I already know that.
Look closer at my other identity.
よく見ろ ワシのもう一つの顔を｡
Huh?
NASA chief pilot instructor?
ＮＡＳＡ主任教官パイロット…
パイロット!?
Pilot?!
日々人に ジェット機の操縦を
叩き込んだのはワシだ｡ハハハ！
I'm the one who taught Hibito how to fly a jet.
Eh?
I told you that I have good control.
言ったろ｡ワシは
コントロールが得意｡ハハハ！
マジかよ…!?
S-Seriously?
宇宙飛行士を目指してる
兄貴ってのは➡
So you must be the big brother who wants to become an astronaut.
お前のことだろう｡お？ムッタ｡
Right, Mutta?
I'm a safe driver on the ground,
(ﾃﾞﾆｰﾙ)ワシは 車は安全運転だが➡
ジェット機となると
ちょいと手荒いぞ｡ハハハ｡
but I get a little wild when I'm in a jet.
Er, wait.
あ いや…車も相当…｡
ムッタ！
That wasn't safe driving...
Mutta.
もしお前が 宇宙飛行士に
選ばれたら次にワシと会うのは…｡
If you're selected as an astronaut, the next time we meet
will be at the airfield.
飛行場だ｡イエーイ！
Yay.
See you around.
(ﾃﾞﾆｰﾙ)じゃあ またな！
犬はちゃんと つないどけ｡
Remember to tie up your dog!
This is crazy...
なんてこった…｡
My right hand spent its days afraid of losing something
but wished to be held by my left hand
I lead you by the hand
Is my hand only there to hold my own hand now?
I can't lose it
Amidst my nagging disappointment that I can do nothing
I felt I wanted to do something
I let go again
I'm not alone in this world
If my hands can only hold two things
then I hope one of them is you
Not alone, not alone
I want our hearts to be connected
I want to be connected
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#32 A Private Place
＜私は
１人 ヒューストンに残って➡
I'm the only one staying in Houston to watch Hibito land on the moon.
日々人の月面着陸を
見守ることに＞
＜そんな中
あずま
先輩飛行士の吾妻さんが➡
That's when I spot the astronaut Azuma with his family.
家族といるところに遭遇する＞
Azuma only smiles when he's with his family.
(ｼﾞｪﾆﾌｧｰ)＜吾妻が笑うのは
家族といる時だけよ｡➡
だから
誰も あの中には入らないわ＞
That's why everyone stays away.
＜あだ名とか付けたら
打ち解けるかな？＞
Maybe we'd get closer if I gave him a nickname.
Like Azu-Azu.
＜アズアズとか…＞
(ｼﾞｪﾆﾌｧｰ)＜はぁ？＞
Huh?
Next time, on Space Brothers:
"A Private Place"
＜吾妻さん 日々人に
先を譲ってくれたんですか？＞
Azuma, did you let Hibito go first?
パンパカパーン！
今週の宇宙写真です！
This Week's Space Photo
Launching a satellite!
This week's space photo!
すっげぇ！
Awesome!